Have seen the merged sort algorithm in animation.
Now let's go and see.
Deeply the merge sort complexity and then try to implement the code in C and in Java later on.
So Merge Sort is one of the most popular sorting algorithms that is based on the principle of divide
and conquer algorithm.
We have, sir, we have watched and learn about the divide and conquer algorithm in the previous videos.
So here is a problem is divided into multiple sub problems.
Each sub problem is solved individually, and finally, sub problems are combined to form the final
solution.
If we see this array, we have divided into two main parts the left and the right, and this left part
have been also divided into two groups six and five two five to 12.
So 512 512 is being also divided and then combined into an ordered array, and we have this part six.
Now, in order to combine them, we start searching, which is sorting from the merge and into from
the parts and merge them into one.
So this is when we combine them, when we merge them.
This is why we have called it merged sort.
So five is less than six.
Six is less than 12.
So we have formed the first part.
The second part is the same, then nine at one.
We have divided the inten into 10 into one single row and nine one.
We divide this into two parts one and nine, and we have sorted by putting one in the beginning and
nine into the second case.
And now we need to combine the one nine sub array and that 10 summary.
We joined them by one nine and then then so we have four and another sorted editing somebody.
Now we need to join these two sub arrays sorted substrates.
So we add one five six nine then and the twelfth.
We add the elements later.
So this is how to solve the problem, how to solve the problem in sub bearnaise.
And then we join and merge the two solution into one solution and form the merged.
So the Merge sort function repeatedly divides the array into two halves until we reach the stage where
we tried to perform, merge, sort on a sub array of size.
One example be equal, equal to offer.
And after that, the merge functions come a function, comes into play and combined the sorted and they
into larger arrays until the whole array is merged.
Merged sort, this is the algorithm that we are going to implement in C and and Joffe.
So if B greater than are, then return, this is the Merge sort that accepts an essay that we are going
to solve and do it too short and b and ah, so it should be greater than ah.
And these are the sub elements, then be greater than, ah, than return.
OK, we have sorted them.
Otherwise, we create queue equal people plus are divided over two.
So we are getting the quotient and we start calling the Merge sort again.
Here we have said that the divide and conquer algorithm is based on three cartoons, so this is the
recursion we have passed that gain a we have best a game B.
And here is the quotient, not art.
We are passing P plus r over two.
So consider this B one, two three over two.
Ah, so one point five.
So we are passing this as the Merge sort.
We need to sort the first element here and in the second step we use Mercer Q Plus one.
You see, guys, this is the algorithm.
And ah, so we net need to make a merge sort for the other part, which is five and 12.
And then we use the method merge that merges B, Q and I.
OK, so this is the algorithm behind Mercer to sort an entire array, we need to call merge, sort a
at and zero and pass a.
As part of me, the array we pass zero fraud index and the links a minus one.
OK.
As this array or this diagram shows at right at index zero and two to three, we pass it and divide
it in two, zero to one and two to three.
As shown in the image that emerged, sort algorithm recursively divides the array into halves until
we reach the base case of array within one element.
This is the base case of one element.
OK.
Then after that, the Merge function picks up the sort that summarize and merge them to gradually sort
the entire area.
We have merged this sub array and we have merged this hurray.
Then we combine them, they how we when we use the Merge sort, so merge sort applications in the inversion
count problem in the external sorting and income e-commerce application.
Let's learn about the complexity before moving into that code implementation and see and next in Java
exercises.
So the time complexity of the Merge sort and the best case scenario it is and that time complexity,
it's old and times look, and in the worst case is and times look and and the average is and time slogan
sorting errors on different machines like sort of merge sort is a recursive algorithm, and time complexity
can be expressed as following a recursion relation at this D of an.
Two to two and minus.
Over two plus set off an.
But since the above recursion and this that occurred, that occurrence can be solved either using the
recurrence three method or the master method, it falls in their case, two of the master method and
the solution of recurrence is Oh, and.
Lug.
And so this would be solved in terms of all of analog.
OK, from this we have we have conclude that the time complexity of merged sort is and look and in three
cases, the worst, average and best as merge, sort always divide, array into two halves and takes
linear time to merge two halves.
And the axillary space complexities of and and stability is.
Yes, there's there's stable.
So this is the merged sort, and it is a very popular algorithm.
Now, let's move to and learn about Merge sort.